<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sample>
    <head><title>Nineteenth Century Collections Online Sample</title> <dateRange>1800-1820</dateRange></head>
<bibl n="1" type="essay">
    <author>
        <name>Anon.</name>
    </author>
    <title level="article">A New and Cheap Paint</title>
    <title level="journal">The Medical Repository</title>
    <printPlace>New York, NY, United States</printPlace>
    <date when="1804|1805">1804-1805</date>
    <passage>"A new, cheap, and lasting paint has been lately invented and successfully applied to gates, rails, and palisadoes...Two coats are to be laid on with a painter's brush; the expense of which will be about a half-penny a square yard."</passage>
    <document>i.116</document>
    <definition>Bearing a low price in proportion to its intrinsic value; of good value in proportion to its price; well worth the price.</definition>
    <partOfSpeech>adjective</partOfSpeech>
</bibl>
    <bibl n="2" type="essay">
        <author>
            <name>Anon.</name>
        </author>
        <title level="article">A Cheap and Excellent Wine</title>
        <title level="journal">The Medical and Agricultural Register</title>
        <printPlace>Boston, MA, United States</printPlace>
        <date when="1806">1806</date>
        <passage>"A cheap and excellent Wine...At the end of six or eight weeks, you will have a liquor, which will not cost more than about twenty-five cents by the gallon, possessing much the taste and sensible qualities of wine, and inferior hardly to none."</passage>
        <document>i.14</document>
        <definition>Bearing a low price in proportion to its intrinsic value; of good value in proportion to its price; well worth the price.</definition>
        <partOfSpeech>adjective</partOfSpeech>
    </bibl>
    <bibl n="3" type="advertisement">
        <author>
            <name>Anon.</name>
        </author>
        <title level="article">Ornamental Hair</title>
        <title level="journal">La Belle Assemblee</title>
        <printPlace>London, United Kingdom</printPlace>
        <date when="1807">1807</date>
        <passage>"For lightness, elegance, and ease, they are unparalleled; fifty percent cheaper than any other house in London; and, for the variety, he can display thousands of tints and shapes, appropriately to heighten the loveliness of youth, or veil the deficiencies of age."</passage>
        <document>i.7 p.72</document>
        <definition>(Applied to the price itself, the place where a commodity is sold, etc.) cheap fare: a fare at a lower rate than the ordinary fare; also cheap rate; also attrib.</definition>
        <partOfSpeech>adjective</partOfSpeech>
    </bibl>
    <bibl n="4" type="essay">
        <author>
            <name>Anon.</name>
        </author>
        <title level="article">Miscellaneous</title>
        <title level="journal">The Lady's Weekly Miscellany</title>
        <printPlace>New York, NY, United States</printPlace>
        <date when="1810">1810</date>
        <passage>"The ornament of Sobriety which comes next to be considered, is by no means a cheap one. But though it be purchased with difficulty, it is lost with ease. To preserve it will require the unremitted exercise of prudence, vigilance, and severe circumspection..."</passage>
        <document>i.4 p.388</document>
        <definition>Involving little trouble and hence of little worth; worthless, paltry.</definition>
        <partOfSpeech>adjective</partOfSpeech>
    </bibl>
    <bibl n="5" type="essay">
        <author>
            <name>Anon.</name>
        </author>
        <title level="article">Recent Publications</title>
        <title level="journal">The New York Medical Inquirer</title>
        <printPlace>New York, NY, United States</printPlace>
        <date when="1810">1810</date>
        <passage>"A late discovery extremely interesting to Planters and Farmers, relative to fertilizing poor and exhausted ground, upon a cheap and easy plan, with some remarks and observations on Orcharding and Gardening."</passage>
        <document>i.146 p.144</document>
        <definition>Costing little labour, trouble, effort, etc.; easily obtained.</definition>
        <partOfSpeech>adjective</partOfSpeech>
    </bibl>
    <bibl n="6" type="book">
        <author>
            <name>
                <surname>More</surname>
                (<forename>Hannah</forename>)</name>
        </author>
        <title level="extended">The Works of Hannah More, Including Several Pieces Never before Published</title>
        <title level="short">The Works of Hannah More</title>
        <printPlace>Philadelphia, PA, United States</printPlace>
        <date when="1813">1813</date>
        <passage>"the poor would get the coarse pieces of meat cheaper, if the the gentle-folks did not buy them for soups and gravy. Mrs Jones thought there was reason in this: so away she went to...the only persons in the parish who could afford to buy these costly things. She told them, that if they would all be so good as to buy only prime pieces, which they could very well afford, the coarse and cheap joints would come more within the reach of the poor."</passage>
        <document>i.171 p.173</document>
        <definition>That may be bought at small cost; bearing a relatively low price; inexpensive. Opposed to dear.</definition>
        <partOfSpeech>adjective</partOfSpeech>
    </bibl>
                </fs>
                
                <fs n="7">
                    <f name="author"></f>
                    <f name="title">The Briton (London, United Kingdom). The Avowed Object of Some of the Reformers of the Present Day Is the Establishment of Atheism or Deism...</f>
                    <f name="date">1819</f>
                    <f name="passage">"The avowed object of some of the Reformers of the present day is the establishment of Atheism or Deism; and the tendency of many of their cheap publications is to ridicule religion and to bring the Bible into contempt. The number of Deistical publications, and the industry with which they are disseminated, must astonish every person; and the probable effects of the perusal of them, must fill every friend of religion with alarm."</f>
                    <f name="image">i.1</f>
                    <f name="definition">
                        <string>Low, poor, disparaging. (adjective)</string>
                        <string>Accounted of small value, made little of, lightly esteemed; esp. brought into contempt through being made too familiar. (adjective)</string>
                    </f> 
                </fs>
                <fs n="8">
                    <f name="author"></f>
                    <f name="title">Caroline, Queen. Papers Relating to Queen Caroline. The Times, London.</f>
                    <f name="date">1820</f>
                    <f name="passage">"Court publications of yesterday, furnish us with the names and abodes of half-a-dozen little knots of address-makers, most of which were already public. With those who have no doubts to satisfy - no differences to trouble them, nor opinions to form, but whose task is simply to obey the injunctions of a master - addresses are as cheap as Christmas pies. It is only to set a single puppet going, and the rest will dance to the same wire. But it really would puzzle any novice to make out the drift of what are nicknamed 'Loyal addresses'."</f>
                    <f name="image">i.175</f>
                    <f name="definition">
                        <string>Involving little trouble and hence of little worth; worthless, paltry. (adjective)</string>
                        <string>Accounted of small value, made little of, lightly esteemed; esp. brought into contempt through being made too familiar. (adjective)</string>
                    </f>
                </fs>
                <fs n="9">
                    <f name="author">Latham, John.</f>
                    <f name="title">On the Medicinal Properties of the Solanum Tuberosum, or Potato Plant</f>
                    <f name="date">1820</f>
                    <f name="passage">"We have many medicines, but few remedies. Of the former, many are expensive exotics, as opium for example; and therefore it would be exceedingly desirable, both in point of economy, and to check the inducements towards adulteration, if substitutes, of easy access and cheap materials, could be procured. This is leaving out of the question the chance or hope of discovering useful properties in the new articles investigated."</f>
                    <f name="image">p.400 i.64</f>
                    <f name="definition">Bearing a low price in proportion to its intrinsic value; of good value in proportion to its price; well worth the price. (adjective)</f>
                </fs>
                <fs n="10">
                    <f name="author">Lady Humdrum, pseud.</f>
                    <f name="title">Domestic scenes: a novel</f>
                    <f name="date">1820</f>
                    <f name="passage">The return of Henry from the Priory entirely relieved Emily's anxieties respecting its inmates; nor could she help being amused with Katty's reliance on the efficacy of her P.S.; and still greater amusement did she afterwards, very contrary to her intnention, afford her invalid, when in her zeal for the school, and ignorance of lacalities, she imparted the commission for cheap flannel.</f>
                    <f name="image">p.5</f>
                    <f name="definition">
                        <string>That may be bought at small cost; bearing a relatively low price; inexpensive. Opposed to dear.</string>
                    </f>
                </fs>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
